<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://chelberserker.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://chelberserker.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-01-25T11:20:32+00:00</updated><id>https://chelberserker.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Egor Bersenev | Scattering in soft matter physics</title><subtitle>Personal web page of Egor A. Bersenev. I am a scientist specializing in application of scattering (X-ray, light and neutron) to problems in soft matter and bio physics. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">SURF Python package is released</title><link href="https://chelberserker.github.io/blog/2026/SURF-release/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SURF Python package is released"/><published>2026-01-02T16:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-02T16:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://chelberserker.github.io/blog/2026/SURF-release</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://chelberserker.github.io/blog/2026/SURF-release/"><![CDATA[<p>I have released a Python package for XRR and GID data analysis. This has organically emerged from my PhD work on the beamline. The main purpose of it is simple and reproducible processing of X-ray reflectivity and Grazing Incidence Diffraction data obtained on the ID10-SURF beamline at ESRF. Main processing pipeline was settled during past few years (2021-2024) with lots of input from Oleg Konovalov (scientist in charge of ID10), Maciej Jankowski (beamline scientist at the time, now software engineer at ESRF) and some beamline users.</p> <p>For the moment it is only focused on ID10-SURF setup, but later other instruments may be implemented, e.g. BM28 XMaS at ESRF. Overall logic follows ESRF data structure, which is NeXuS compliant, when generated with BLISS. In principle, it can be adapted to be used with EWOKS software to initiate processing in real time.</p> <p>The package can be installed via pip:</p> <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>pip <span class="nb">install </span>esrf-id10-surf
</code></pre></div></div> <p>If you fancy making changes to the code to facilitate your specific analysis, then package can be installed in the modifiable way:</p> <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>git clone https://github.com/chelberserker/ESRF_ID10_SURF
<span class="nb">cd </span>ESRF_ID10_SURF
pip <span class="nb">install</span> <span class="nt">-e</span> <span class="nb">.</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Package also provides a batch processing through command line script.</p> <p>Code is available freely on my <a href="https://github.com/chelberserker/ESRF_ID10_SURF">GitHub</a> and is distributed through MIT license. API documentation is hosted <a href="https://chelberserker.github.io/ESRF_ID10_SURF">here</a> and will be updated</p> <p>I have described operation of the soft in <a href="https://chelberserker.github.io/ESRF_ID10_SURF">documentation</a> and in a <a href="/_projects/1_project_SURF.md">blog post</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="software"/><category term="XRR"/><category term="GID"/><category term="python"/><category term="software"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Release of a software package for Surface X-ray scattering processing]]></summary></entry></feed>